A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Harry E. Wilhelm FA628
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Latin America and the Caribbean, Office Files of Harry E. Wilhelm
1965-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wilhelm, Harry E.
Ford Foundation
FA628
3.52 Cubic Feet
These papers from the Office of Harry E. Wilhelm cover the years 1965 to 1970, while Mr. Wilhelm was the New York-based Director of the Office for Latin America and the Caribbean. They are arranged in three series. The papers consist primarily of chronological files and confidential correspondence. Also included in the papers is some of Wilhelm's chronological files that were retained by his Senior Staff Assistant [1966 - 1967?], Catharine A. Olson. She used the initials "CAPO" to identify the files which she maintained.
Biographical / Historical
Harry E. Wilhelm, Director of the Latin American and Caribbean Program from February 1965 to December 1970, also held the following positions at the Foundation:
- January 1971, Representative, India and Nepal
- February 1963, Representative, Argentina and Chile
- October 1961, Program Associate, South and Southeast Asia Program
- October 1959, Assistant Representative, Burma
- November 1957, Assistant to the Representative, Burma
(N.B.: In Jan 1967, the program organization of the Foundation was restructured. At this time, the Latin America and Caribbean Program became part of the International Division. Wilhelm's title was changed to Head, Latin America and the Caribbean).
On December 18, 1975 Wilhelm resigned from the Foundation.
Harry E. Wilhelm was born on August 21, 1928. He received his A.B. in Political Science and English from Ohio Wesleyan University and his M.P.A. in Public and International Affairs from the Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs at Princeton University.
Prior to joining the Foundation, Wilhelm held several positions in the Executive Office of the President of the United States' Bureau of the Budget. In 1969, while Head of the Foundation's Latin American and Caribbean Program, Wilhelm served on evaluation committees of the Organization of American States and of the National Academy of Sciences, respectively.
Scope and Contents
These papers from the Office of Harry Wilhelm cover the years 1965 to 1970, during which time Mr. Wilhelm was Director of the Latin American and Caribbean (LAC) program in New York. They are divided into three series. Series I, CHRONOLOGICAL FILES, contains Mr. Wilhelm's copy of his correspondence to persons outside the Foundation, as well as his copy of his correspondence, memoranda and telegrams to Ford Foundation staff. This series is available to all researchers. Series II, CONFIDENTIAL CORRESPONDENCE, contains inter-office memoranda, correspondence, telexes and telegrams. Series III, "CAPO CONFIDENTIAL" CHRONOLOGICAL FILES, are Wilhelm's 1966 to 1967 chronological files that were retained by Catherine A. Olson, Mr. Wilhelm's Senior Staff Assistant. Access to Series II and III is available to internal staff only, and only with the permission of the Archivist, because these series contain sensitive personnel-related material. It should be noted that within the three series there is a fair amount of duplicate material. These duplicates have been kept in the folders so as to maintain the papers in the order in which they were received by the Archives.
Arrangement
The Latin America and Caribbean Papers of Harry E. Wilhelm, are divided into three series:
I. Chronological Files, March 1966 to April 1970, consists of 2' of material.
II. Confidential Correspondence, February 1965 - December 1970, consists of 1' of material.
III. "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, April 1966 - February 1967, consists of .5' of material.
Separated Materials
Papers falling into the following categories were removed from all three series and placed with the appropriate files in the Ford Foundation Archives:
- Staff and consultant reports
- Annual reports on the activities of the LAC program
- Budget papers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Chronological Files, 1966-1970; I
  Arrangement
  Series I, Chronological Files (March 1966 to April 1970), is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Chronological Files, consists of Wilhelm's copy of his outgoing correspondence to persons outside the Foundation, as well as his copy of his correspondence to Foundation staff and of his memoranda to the files. The material in this series provides an overview of the Foundation's interests in Latin America and the Caribbean for the years 1965 to 1970, and demonstrates that one of the Foundation's overriding goals in Latin America was to improve the caliber of higher education throughout the region. There are memoranda concerning the 1965 grant (PA65-327) to the International Institute of Education to strengthen the University of Chile through an exchange program with the University of California. Another dominant Foundation interest was agricultural development. There are memoranda and discussion outlines which document the early stages of the Foundation's collaboration with the Rockefeller Foundation in the development of international agricultural centers in Latin America (Log 66-88). This series also contains material concerning the Action Committee for Latin American Integration (Log 67-210). There is some memoranda concerning the involvement of the late Senator Jacob Javits in this project. Material relating to personnel policies, administrative procedures, fiscal year program budgets, and overall program planning for the LAC office is also filed in this series.
  - Chronological Files, 1970 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 February 17-27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 February 2-16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 1970 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 September 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 September 3-15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 August (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 May 16-29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 May 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 April 16-30 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 April 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 March 11-28 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 March 3-10 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 February 24-28 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 February 3-20 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 January 17-31 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Chronological Files, 1969 January 2-16 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 December (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 November (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 October 15-31 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 October 1-14 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 September 17-30 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 September 3-12 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 August 19-30 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 August 1-16 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 July 15-31 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 July 1-12 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 June (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 May 15-29 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 May 1-14 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 April 19-30 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 April 1-18 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 March 13-29 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 March 1-12 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 February (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 January 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Chronological Files, 1968 January 2-15 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 December (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 November 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 November 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 October (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 September (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 August (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 July 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 July 5-14 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 June 12-30 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 June 1-9 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 May 16-31 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 May 1-15 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 April 17-28 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 April 3-14 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 March (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 February 14-20 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 February 1-13 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Chronological Files, 1967 January (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 December (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 November (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 October 20-31 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 October 3-19 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 September 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 September 1-16 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 August 16-31 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 August 1-15 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 July (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 June 16-30 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 June 2-15 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 May (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 April (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Chronological Files, 1966 March (Box 5, Folder 75)
- Confidential Correspondence, 1965-1970; II
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series II Confidential Correspondence is restricted from scholarly research. All contents of this series is closed.
  Series II, Confidential Correspondence (February 1965 - December 1970), is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  The bulk of Series II, Confidential Correspondence, is the inter-office memoranda that were exchanged among Mr. Wilhelm in New York, and the Foundation's field office staffs in Latin America and the Caribbean. These memoranda deal primarily with the organization and staffing of the LAC program, and include a considerable amount of personnel-related information such as staff evaluations and salary recommendations. Roughly one quarter of the inter-office correspondence in this series duplicates the grantee-related inter-office correspondence in Series I, Chronological Files.
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 August 24-December 10 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    Restricted from scholarly research.
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 May 1-August 12 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 February 9-April 21 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1970 January 5-31 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 July 1-December 24 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 May 1-June 27 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 February 17-April 30 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1969 January 3-24 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 September 4-December 27 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 August 6-30 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 May 8-July 25 (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1968 January 31-April 17 (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 September 8-December 28 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 June 5-August 22 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 April 14-May 31 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1967 January 17-April 3 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 October 4-December 20 (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 June 6-September 27 (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 April 1-May 30 (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1966 January 4-March 17 (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 October 1-December 17 (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 September 4-23 (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 May 3-July 30 (Box 7, Folder 98)
  - Confidential Correspondence, 1965 February 4-April 28 (Box 7, Folder 99)
- "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966-1967; III
  Series III, "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files (April 1966 - February 1967), is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  Series III is restricted from scholarly research. All contents of this series is closed.
  Series III, "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, consists of copies of that portion of Mr. Wilhelm's 1966 to 1967 outgoing correspondence which was deemed confidential or personal by his Senior Staff assistant, Catharine A. Olson. This series contains 1967 and 1968 program budget and planning material, as well as material relating to the Overseas Development Self Study, conducted in the fall of 1966. Almost one half of the material in this series duplicates the material in Series II.
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1967 February 2-April 3 (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1967 January 5-30 (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 December 2-22 (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 October 4-31 (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 August 4-September 30 (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 May 2-July 20 (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - "CAPO Confidential" Chronological Files, 1966 February 28-April 25 (Box 8, Folder 106)
- Appendix B: Ford Foundation LAC Field Office Staff, 1965-1970
  Appendix B: Ford Foundation LAC Field Office Staff, 1965 - 1970
  The following is a list of field office representatives for Latin America and the Caribbean for the years 1965 to 1970. The papers of Harry Wilhelm include memoranda and correspondence to and from these staff members:
  1965 Buenos Aires - John Nagel Santiago - John Nagel Rio de Janeiro - S. Widdicombe Mexico City - Robert Wickham Caracas - Robert Wickham Central America - Robert Wickham Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - Peter Fraenkel
  1966 Buenos Aires - John Nagel Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - S. Widdicombe Mexico City - William Gamble Central America - William Gamble Caracas - Roy Crawley Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - William Cotter
  1967 Buenos Aires - John Nagel Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - S. Widdicombe Mexico City - William Gamble Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - William Cotter Caribbean - John Hilliard
  1968 Buenos Aires - Richard Adams* Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - W. Carmichael Mexico City - William Gamble Lima - Peter Fraenkel Bogota - William Cotter Jamaica - James Trowbridge*
  1969 Buenos Aires - Rey Carlson Santiago - John Netherton Rio de Janeiro - W. Carmichael Mexico City - William Gamble Caribbean - William Gamble Central America - William Gamble Jamaica - James Trowbridge** Lima - Abe Lowenthal*** Bogota - William Cotter
  1970 Buenos Aires - Rey Carlson Santiago - Peter Bell Rio de Janeiro - W. Carmichael Mexico City - John Funari Caribbean - John Funari Central America - John Funari Jamaica - James Trowbridge** Lima - Richard Dye Bogota - William Gamble
  * Program Advisor ** Assistant Representative *** Acting Representative